all right hello and welcome it's May
30th 2024 and we're in act imp guest
stream
84.1 this will be a presentation and a
discussion with Jesse G so Jesse thank
you for joining and for your
participation looking forward to a great
presentation and then we'll check the
live chat
and see where it goes from
there go for it all right thank you so
much for letting me do this showcase uh
largely what I'm going to go over is
basically an overview uh debut
publication of a series of papers that
have to do with uh habits and uh
adaptive learning in regards to agential
systems and basic
basically uh looking at agential systems
largely from uh the point of view of
biological organisms largely trying to
understand better understand connecting
that with human
behavior and
largely the motivation here for this
series of
Publications it uh started with looking
at a at a um sort of literature review
that was Data focused on looking at the
uh not necessarily
addiction uh from a more broad point of
view but from a drug dependency point of
view when I reached out to a colleague
of mine a number of years
ago uh well little over three years ago
now in 2021 when I first
started uh this journey so so this uh
whole
uh this whole series of work has been
undergone for about slightly over three
years now so I started this work in 2021
originally I was connected indirectly
with a group of graduate
students uh at a state univ work uh
associated with a State
University and they were looking at data
on uh on addiction um not not really
broadly speaking but uh dealing with um
looking at more so drug dependency based
addiction and I was a bit I was quite
disappointed with the effort put into
the paper I mean I understand that the
the students involved were uh were uh
students in data science and informatics
so but at at the same time I was a bit
dismayed by the approach in the paper
and I provided a critique of their work
and I thought to myself well wow like
addiction has some root there's some
root to addiction we need to better
understand and and what's also uh what
was also
um came off quite
um odd to me for a number of years now
is just the The Narrative looking at the
lens of like what is the root of
addictive behavior and that kind of goes
back fun know thinking about
fundamentals um and fundamentally we we
think about habits and when people think
about habits uh mostly stereotypically
again uh people think about habits in
sort of a a bad point of like you know
habits are bad you know point of view
and again reapo fundamentals and
breaking the
stereotypes
[Music]
um I think it's important to understand
okay well our habits good or bad what
can we say about them and how do we
adapt to circumstances that we face as
as humans you know as human beings um
more specifically uh thinking about
about um sort of uh this idea of not
necessarily coping but rein reinforcing
our fitness uh in the sense of like how
can we better engage with the world
around us and with each other and
ourselves most importantly over time
over the course of a
lifetime uh and um so that's been the
general focus of this series of of of
works is trying to look into
uh in terms of adaptive
learning um what interventionary
approaches like what primary
interventionary interventionary
approaches which I'll get into a little
later um can be leveraged to be
reinforcing towards our behavior and
compliment how we engage with the world
around us each other and ourselves
rather than be
counterintuitive um and looking at is
sort of
like kind of like an EB and flow uh of
what where like how we drive how we how
we motivate and direct our
behaviors um so habits can be good or
bad but more so thinking about habits on
a spectrum of being reinforcement based
in a sense that it complements our uh
our fitness and how we engage with each
other in a constructive way in the world
around us of course uh as well as our
our El uh rather than counterintuitive
or
maladaptive um so um anyway I didn't
really give a former a more formal
introduction of of who I am I wanted to
kind of give start with a bit of an
overview of motivation and and drive of
the work I'm
doing um so uh I call myself an
independent researcher I'm working on a
portfolio uh of of work where I spend
quite a bit of time investigating
academic Li literature um I I had for
for this series of Publications I'm
working on I have I have roughly about
uh close to a thousand maybe
little close to a thousand papers that
uh to work
with um I have hundreds of papers that
I've I've I I found that uh I've read
abstracts for that I haven't given a
good read yet but I but I read quite
I've gone through quite a bit of papers
and um it gets to a point where you have
so you find so much work to work with
that you kind of have to figure you kind
of have to prioritize okay do I have
enough content um and um anyway um so
basically what I'm trying to do with the
portfolio work I'm doing is I I I look
for data um I also find a lot of
literature so I think it's important to
find not just data but information
criteria that tells a a story about the
data that's out there um and I I I could
go on a tangent about uh my you know the
limitations of data science
oriented oriented communities not really
telling much of a narrative rather than
looking at the data so what what I try
to do with the work I'm doing is um I
try to find a lot enough
criteria which I consider to be
information or or literature so I find a
whole lot of criteria that emphasizes on
on model building and construction not
just looking at data but um data is
important and um but more importantly
like connecting uh you know building
models not just about the data but being
able to uh tell a story about the
direction in which if we collect data in
a sufficient manner where that would go
where you know where you know uh the
models would tell us uh like you
know what does the information tell us
in terms of that evaluates the criteria
of data and the models that we that we
build
to have an understanding Narrative of
uh um you know uh what we're working
with in terms of uh uh in this case what
I'm working on the series of papers
dealing with habits and adaptive
learning uh really getting to the root
of the problem domain that we're working
with here um and uh so basically what
I'm trying to do again is um you know
build models M mainly complex systems
based models and um work with whatever
data I can um to to to provide a
narrative and and provide a means to
justify
okay this is the problem domain we're
looking at this is how we should
evaluate based on the the criteria or
the the literature that has that has
elaborated on on on the problem domain
take the converging aspects of the
literature so in this case looking at
habits and and adaptive
learning um
and um you know providing emphasis of
like okay this is where we can go based
on the problem domain so that's B
essentially what I'm trying to do
whether or not um you know I end up
working in Academia or industry in in
some way or another um what I feel like
I'm doing is more analytical like
analytics based um not necessarily
engineering focused although uh I am
working on systems based approaches in
terms of um
interventionary uh um means to deal with
adaptive learning and habits which is
not the current paper I'm I'm
elaborating on although um that's that's
going to be the next paper but um I
might get into that a little bit uh a
little later but in a nutshell um even
though that might be a bit of an
elongated explanation about who you know
who I am what I'm trying to do um I'm
also trying to be agnostic about
explaining what I'm trying to do not
like even though I feel like I have an
interest leaning into the cognitive
Sciences given that's largely the uh the
arena that this this paper is is is
leaning is geared towards is is the
cognitive Sciences domain and Ag gental
Systems um I don't want to limit myself
in in a corner per se I I I like to be
open about my capacities of of building
models looking at criteria looking at
data and um provide in uh you know an
evaluation of problem domains we are
investigating anyway so the whole
purpose of this talk now um is to go
over my debut publication work which is
an over more of an
overview of understanding habits and
adaptive learning with regard to
agential systems uh there are four
primary paradigms of interventionary
approaches to Leverage adaptive learning
uh with respect to human behavior U I'll
go over that a little bit U maybe
towards the end uh of the points I'm
making but um what I plan on doing um
I'll present a a base model that I put
together uh and uh momentarily but I'm
going to step through the paper a bit
because there's there's a lot of context
um but um I'm going to try and summarize
the uh the points that I make I um for
those of you who have looked at my work
um I will say that uh it is quite a long
paper so there is this metaanalysis
approach to to the work in in terms of
uh you know looking at a lot of
literature that talk about habits and uh
talks about Ag gental Systems and
different models of of
understanding um perception action uh
perception based Dynamics and and we
engage with the world around us and how
we
anticipate uh you know how we anticipate
how to to leverage engagement over time
based on our history of Engagement so
anyway let let's let's start with the
abstract and and we'll we'll we'll build
up even further so uh like I mentioned
uh this paper presents itself as an
overview of looking at uh understanding
the nature of habits and adaptive
learning with respect to AG gental
Systems so we can uh the best way to
understand what a habit is is a
persisting composition of
behaviors that uh that are that are that
couple our our engagement to to to
leverage um how we
reinforce uh uh interaction with our
envir with our surrounding
environment and um with other
agents as as well as ourselves right um
so on on the one hand uh agents can
engage with their environment in a way
that's constructive uh as well as each
other and themselves uh so we call that
reinforcement learning right where uh
agents are are engaging in in a way
that's constructive to optimize Fitness
probably buffer in the best case buffer
their
Fitness um but uh on the other hand uh
agents also can engage with their
environment in the means that's could be
deceptive or counterintuitive that that
could not only deceive themselves but
other agents in in in the environment
right uh so that has to do with Mal
adaptive learning so we can think of uh
reinforcement learning being on one side
of a spectrum and maladaptive learning
being on the other side of a spectrum
right and and we can say
realistically that uh there's no truly
completely uh you know uh there's no
certain behav you know there's there's
not no there's no most optimal Behavior
that's going to completely optimize the
fitness of an organism or or as as as a
multi-agent
systems um given uh the problems with
cell cellular syence and aging that over
time we engage with the world around us
more suboptimally but um The Challenge
there being that U to optimize Fitness
in the face of uh thinking of of of
aging and cellular
inessence uh being a
problem uh that we don't you know we're
mortal beings agents don't last forever
we break down um we decompose right so
um um in in the face of of that issue of
like becoming more suboptimal over time
reinforcement learning uh leverages
optimizing in in in the and as time goes
on while U maladaptive learning is is
really working
against um the the the optimal means in
which we can leverage Fitness
um
so the paper is pretty comprehensive and
and the reason why it is is a bit long
is one like I mentioned it's more it's
looking at a whole bunch of literature
connecting
ideas uh and
uh um and uh
so I tried to approach the the content
the the
textualization of of of of the paper in
a way that um is both comp you know
comprehensive in terms of uh the
audience that I expect to be a more
General General audience to to be to be
reading it um I'm I'm not too confident
in terms of like how many actual
cognitive scientists neuroscientists or
physicists or whatever are going to be
looking at the paper as opposed to more
Layman type so I try to be mindful about
who's looking at or who is who's going
to be reading the paper and I try to be
comprehensive as much as I can so there
there is some redundancy here and there
in terms of my elaborations on on
specific points especially talking about
perceiving acting and
anticipating uh the world around us like
this idea of what I call the pap cycle
which I constantly bring up uh in in my
work uh well in this particular paper so
we could think of the pap cycle as
perceiving acting a perception action
priers so perception has to do with um
so before elaborating on what I'd call
the pap
cycle
um so as
agents we're constantly like engaging
with stimulus so any any anything that
uh anything that provoke anything that
provokes engagement for agents so agents
we can think of as um single so we can
think of the scaling of Ag gental
Systems to be on the one hand units of
Agents or single
agents H so like single celled organisms
you know your
bacteria your and different types of
cells and all that stuff like simple
cells that don't have much degrees of of
freedom in agency because uh they they
they have simple functions and they
serve simple roles in the in in their in
the environment that they're embedded in
which will get more into this this idea
of how agents are existentially bound
bounded to an embedded environment in in
which they
co-inhabit uh so now on the one one hand
you we have these single agent systems
that have simple functions and uh they
serve a certain role within the
environment they're embedded in and on
the other hand we have compositions of
single agents that make up what uh uh
make up a multicellular system so in
terms of speaking about agency I'm
largely going to talk about and agential
systems in general I'm largely going to
focus on biolog iCal systems and and to
be frank and I do kind of emphasize this
maybe somewhat bluntly uh in my work uh
uh
realistically our most comprehensive and
intuitive understanding of Agents really
is reflective in biology in terms of uh
um you know uh there they really uh you
know you could say that there are very
simple
synthetic uh agential systems uh being
uh uh researched by groups like uh Neil
Gershen feld's Lab at MIT for instance
uh Michael Levan uh Michael Levan's lab
uh also investigates uh uh xenobots and
and and what have you but but but
Michael Lev's work is of course more is
focused fed on biological organisms as
agents um so um so I guess the one
crutch of understanding Ag ental Systems
really is that we're kind of limited to
the scope of understanding Ag ental
Systems in the scope of biology um so
that's kind of the framework that that
I'm focused on here even though I do pay
a little mind of like comparing okay
well computer systems that we' built
using techn our understanding of
Technology uh well very briefly I I do
touch on that uh as opposed to what we
consider to be Ag gental
Systems um now um okay
so what separates a computer you know
the a computer system from an agal
system um is that uh uh we are
constantly engaging with stimulants as I
as I mentioned
uh now stimulus is is really uh you know
anything that immediate that that that
is directly you know anything that
directly provokes engagement of the
agent right so like whether it's
something visual whether um that deals
with any of of the Capa any capacity any
modality for the agent to to to to have
a capacity to develop some kind of
sensation as as a result of being uh
being provoked by the stimulus where
like you could think of the stimulus as
like B like constantly bombarding um uh
the the agent in question right like the
stimulus kind of is like this continuous
input uh that um where the agent has
multiple
modalities of trying to process that
input as Sensations and we're going to
talk about what I call
generalizations uh generalizations of
Sensations so there's kind of multiple
layers here in which Sensations are are
processed by the agent uh so in in line
with what I call the pap cycle uh
perceptions actions and priors so
perceptions deals with this uh capacity
of of enveloping a p perceiving the
stimulus so so so so there's this uh
initial there's this layer of perceiving
stimuli um where the agent again you
know is you know is constantly um uh you
so so so the agent within this embedded
environment that it's existentially
bound to is constantly being bombarded
by stimulus right there there's constant
uh uh constant uh
exposure to to stimulus stimulus is
inevitably uh uh uh directed towards the
to towards the agent and then there's
multiple modalities in which the agent
then tries to process the stimulus as
the stimulus is directed towards the
agent and and the agent has a various
number ways to try to process that
stimulus and what and we can think about
those modalities in the human sense as
like our different senses so Vision
touch uh
auditory taste right um we can think of
like like the combination of sensory
modalities as a means to try to
generalize uh uh how to process these
Sensations in a visceral in so in so the
generalization of Sensations aspect is
this
visceral initially this visceral
processing of
Sensations um so so you could think of
like this visceral processing to be the
the the initial
layer of which that um the agent tries
to process uh these Sensations trying to
like this is kind of where the agent
filters uh what what what it would try
to try to um
try to
uh to distinguish between what is noise
in the environment like what what the
agent should should or should not
prioritize attention
to uh as opposed to what what could be
significant to the agent like what what
what what are what what sorts of
stimulus that are being fed into the
agents um modalities of processing um
you know what stimulus matters and what
stimulus doesn't matter um so this so so
through the through through the
generalization of Sensations there's
this filtering of okay what what matters
and what doesn't matter based on my
circumstances of of leveraging Fitness
as an agent Moment by moment um you know
how do I handle that as an
agent uh
so and
[Music]
um going from there once the agent is
able to prioritize once the agent
recognizes certain patterns of stimulus
that matter then there's this there's
this means to categorize that stimulus
as
information so so so now then uh from
there the agent might additionally try
to Prior prioritize that information
okay what information
matters uh you know there might be
redundant information or there might be
information that matters to to my
fitness right so we we can think about
how that the information now that we
have that is that went through that
General that layer of being generalized
as a sensation and differing
differentiating trying to trying to
understand understand whether that
sensation is just like noise that can't
really be pattern you know we can't be
categorized as as something that might
be redundantly meaningful in some some
sense or it's something recognizable to
the agent but not
meaningful um or
uh okay right so so from this
generalization of Sensations we get to
the point where um the agent is trying
to figure out uh trying to figure out uh
if there's a pattern to distinguish you
know between okay well is this just just
noise that I can't really comprehend and
is therefore not meaningful or is there
some pattern here that provides some
information about my environment and my
circumstances and then by providing some
okay okay now I have information now I
have this generalization of
information um now I speak of the term
generalization because that kind of
leads to the problem of uh what I like
to call Ver veridical perception that um
and a lot of a lot of uh a lot of a lot
of uh researchers and what have you talk
about
illusionism that in the sense that um
we can have a more General a more we can
develop a a gen we can always have a
generalization that it e either is more
becomes more intuitive or or becomes
counterintuitive to how we leverage
circumstance but we never have an
absolute understanding of the
information and and the uh as well as
our
experiences uh which is which is sort of
a problem with with with philosop in the
philosophy of science with okay well how
do we evaluate something to be a theory
as opposed to a conjecture which really
has to do with with the rigor involved
and what have you but um the problem
with veridical perception is we are
always constricted to a relative
understanding of reality in which um an
average an you know if if if enough
agents agree with a a generalization
then that generalization guides a you
know a sufficiently large group of
Agents so uh we can think about the
direction of how we uh develop
Technologies and how modern civilization
got to where it is today and we're going
to talk more about inter agent Dynamics
uh momentarily but um the idea is that
um we're constantly generalizing world
around us we
and uh there there's and and even though
we can come up with generalizations
which many which most of us could
largely agree with those generalizations
could be challenged by uh looking
through a different lens of of
generalizing that criteria so it's sort
of a paradox of like okay well how do we
evaluate the Cris criteria that we have
as knowledge when you know we we have
sort of these best guesss so to speak of
of understanding uh what's happening
with the world around us and how we
understand reality and how we engage
with each other um how we develop
Technologies uh but um anyway um okay
so going back to understanding habits
and and what they have to do with um
with
Behavior Uh again I talk about uh you
know I I talk about habits being these
persistent compositions of of behavior
and um on the one hand um we have
Dynamics pertaining to Nature and d uh
of of the agent and the nurturing of the
agent right so we think about nature
versus nurture now
um so nature pertains to phys
physiological
limitations while uh nurture pertains to
the exposure over time so we could think
of like the you know the course of a
lifetime an agent is exposed to
environmental
circumstances and um there's this idea
of intrinsic and extrinsic variability
of circumstances of of environment so uh
we can think on the one hand that as
multi-agent systems being human beings
um we uh we we are a whole ecosystem
right we are composed of multiple cells
and we have these different anatomical
layers uh that uh that allow us to have
this integrated
functionality in which we uh leverage
metabolic and Cog cognitive low uh now
the key thing to understand here about
metabolic and cognitive load is um is
top is the top down as opposed to bottom
up Dynamics in which agents facilitate
their own
Integrity um as as a m um and and we're
speaking largely about multi-agent
systems because um uh there's this
complexification of behavior that
enables the capacity of for instance our
ability to make decisions because we
have a central nervous system not all
organisms have a central nervous system
right um so we especially when we think
about the single agent systems they're
much more simple in function they have
much lesser degree of of
agency since we're composed of multiple
cells and all these different subsystems
that regulate functioning uh that deals
with metabolic
cost um that gives us a bit more degrees
of freedom because there's all there's
all these these these different
subsystems engaging with each other that
facilitate the uh the capacities we have
to engage with the world around us so on
the one hand uh thinking from bottom up
Dynamics uh we have the the composition
of cells that compose of different organ
systems right that uh regulate metabolic
load um that enables the possibility
from the top down for when we think of
cognitive load from the top down we're
thinking about executive functioning um
so so from top down Dynamics uh we're
thinking about um how cognitive load is
facilitated where decision making
happens
um and this we we'll talk more about uh
the the uh what is um fundamental to
this decision making
momentarily U but
um thinking about nature Dynamics we're
thinking about the physiological
limitations of of the Integrity uh of
bodily functions from the bottom up that
influence the top down Dynamics uh that
facil itate cognitive load leverage
right so so so problems with
physiology uh has has to do like maybe
maybe with with uh problems with with
with uh you know from from the beginning
of of the agent's life cycle or at some
point there's some hindrance that that
uh
sticks uh that kind of sticks out as as
like a barrier for the agent to to
leverage um how they engage with their
environment whether or not you know
let's say uh uh an amputated limb for
instance like I you know like like I
like if I lost my arm like how is that
gonna impact how I engage with the world
around me right or something more severe
than that right so on the one hand we
think about physiological limitations
pertaining to nurture Dynamics uh we can
think of like the the the beginning life
of the life cycle an agent like
considering birth problems problems from
birth or we can think think of like
something that just
happened that could be an existential
hindrance that could be permanent or or
pretty long lasting until that that
hindrance is corrected um whether or not
it could be corrected and and in terms
of nurture Dynamics since nurture
Dynamics have uh uh uh you know pertain
to the course of a lifetime exposure
uh in which an agent leverages how uh it
interacts with its surrounding
environment other agents and
intrinsically and extrinsically of
course thinking about how the agent
deals with its its
own uh uh its own internalizations and
externalizations as well as considering
how it engages with other agents and it
surrounding
environment um and and the nurture
Dynamics have uh generally would have
the most impact because it deals with
the full life cycle of the agent right
so like you know until the agent ceases
to exist it's going to be constantly
engaging with an environment which it's
bound to and it's constantly going to
engage with other agents and and the the
exposure Dynamics are are what are what
is Central to this engagement and um
both intr intrinsically and
extrinsically right um and now um I was
talking about metabolic load um I and uh
now uh like every function of an a of of
the agent um like every every process
that happens like every interaction you
know when we think about this you know
from the Single Cell level to the
multicellular level of of the um
Integrity of of different functions of
the agent from the bottom up from sorry
from from from the uh um the top down to
the bottom
up um all that involves metabolic load
and I even argue that the the process of
of having thoughts that that like even
generating thoughts in our head even in
in a way that's compulsive or you know
thoughts that that just kind of go in
and out or or you know other processes
like that involve perception action and
priors all that comes down to metabolic
load
processing um and and those metabolic
Dynamics are are facilitated through you
know um are largely uh facilitated from
the bottom from from you know from the
bottom up um you know in terms of of of
of of the integrity at at scale
um okay so let's move on to
routines um being fundamental so rout
rou Ines uh we can think of uh R
routines like you know for those of you
who are programmers or or have a
programming or engineering background we
can think of a routine as like some kind
of instruction or or or or or some kind
of a a simple instruction among other uh
instructions that enable Behavior to
happen right and and we can also think
of routines as uh compositions
of uh uh you know this this
continual uh we can also think of
routines as the enabling of persistence
to happen right so on the on the one
hand you know we can think of routine as
uh you know part some aspect of the
Behavior Uh on the other hand we can
also think of
U more more more so I contextualize
routines to be um the means in which the
persistence uh uh of a be of of some
compositions that make up a
habit right to be to to be able to be
orchestrated because the because a habit
you can think of of a habit to be some
routine uh um some routine
characteristic of which the agent is act
is leveraging
um in some procedural orchestrated
fashion right um that that some that
that either um uh
constructively optimizes its Fitness or
or maintains its its its current state
of Fitness in a way that right when we
think about optimizing on the
reinforcement aspect uh re terms of
reinforcement learning or being counter
you know routines and uh like this
routinization of behavior of habits um
you know could could be counterintuitive
to the agent too right um like this
Persistence of of behavior could be
counterintuitive uh to to the behav
behavior of Agents as well and and and
and we this
regulation uh of
uh now now this regulation of of
behavior uh we we we can think of is not
not static right you know like it you
know we're not consistently in the same
state when we're engaging with our
environment because the environment that
we are embedded in is not in a fixed
State either so the environment as well
as ourselves as agents are not in a
static state so we're like these D we're
these
complex uh adaptive dynamical systems
complex in the sense that uh we have you
know we're composed of uh uh you know
like I mentioned like we're we're
composed of multip we're these
multicellular systems where we're a
whole environment ecosystem have you but
we're we we are composed of all these
integ integral functions that regulate
an entire
system um so that's on the complex
complex
side um and then adaptive being that
system is trying to
compensate a a way to regulate Behavior
based on circumstances right whether or
not the
circumstances uh optimize or or deceive
the organ or deceive the
agent so that that that's that's what
what I mean in terms of thinking about
uh comp you know agents as complex
adaptive systems that uh you know know
we're we are these these compositional
systems that uh have certain um exhibit
certain behaviors in a means that try to
uh
regulate uh our capacity to engage with
with our environment and in the sense of
you know thinking intrinsically uh
regulating our own our our own bodily
functioning and cognitive functioning as
well as you know extrinsically as well
how we engage with our surrounding
environment um as well as other agents
because those other agents are part of
the surrounding environment and we're
part of the environment as well hence
we're we are embedded in in this
environment
right so um obviously we can think of
this uh you know the reinforcement
learning as opposed to Mal adaptive
learning capacity of agents to be like
sort of a tug
OFW um you know hustle in terms of like
optimizing as opposed to deceiving
Fitness right because on the one hand
there there are moments in which we can
optimize leverage in which we can
strategize certain mean certain you know
ways to reinforce our behaviors and and
those ways could themselves become
counterintuitive over time based on how
circumstances might change uh because
the environment is not in a static State
it's it's in this you know we're in this
we exist within a complex system as
complex systems right that are are are
are are changing State over time due to
to due to
um uh you know the you know the state uh
of which the uh entire environment you
know like what you know the resources in
the environment available to agents to
to utilize you know whether or not how
do resources remain available how those
res you know uh those resources might
change and and how other agents might
change their behavior or conduct
themselves as well as
ourselves um and
so you know we're we're always trying
you know as agents we're always trying
you know we're we're we you know I don't
want to use the word exploit as a bad
word but we we are uh trying to figure
out a way to leverage resources and you
know you know what can we use as
resources in our environment optimize
metabolism you know to to optimize our
bodily functioning capacities from the
bottom up to the top down as well as uh
this idea of uh utilizing certain
aspects of the environment as tools and
and developing Technologies and
communicating with with other
agents um as as well
well uh all right
so as agents we we have this gold
directedness and
orientation and this this routine
Behavior like this like the persistent
dynamics of habits and just kind of like
thinking of of of habits as like like
these reoccurring behav ways um or uh
these ways that we repetitively engage
with uh
with uh with our environment and other
agents and even ourselves the way we
kind of engage with our ourselves and
like how we start our day and how we end
our day how we you know we work on tasks
and all that uh thinking about human
behavior um uh so and and that is like
you know there that's aligned with uh
you know this engagement is is in line
with uh you know this you know when we
think of goal orientation
we're thinking about uh you know how an
agent kind of facilitates you know
thinking about okay I'm going to do this
to to achieve this or or or get this
resource you like I want to have this
resource I have to to do a certain
number of things um so goal directedness
could be you know composed of a subset
of goals or there's change in in you
know there are dynamics and you know the
goals themselves are not necessarily
static but uh in terms of like
instinctual goals like we have to
maintain metabolic load sufficiently for
for our integrity right so so we can
think of like there's certain certain
goals that are are primary that
facilitate um how we optimize Fitness
like you know eating eat you know
dieting uh exercise you know well
thinking about human behavior we think
about like stuff like dieting exercise
sleep uh drinking water hydration like
what what you know what are what are
fundamental uh fundamental goals that
are going to
regulate inte you know this integral uh
integrated
um uh functioning uh from bottom
facilitating bottom up and and top down
facilitation in which an agent
leverages uh optimizing Fitness right so
so when we think about gold directing
this we're really thinking we're really
talking about okay how how is the agent
uh optimizing its Integrity you know
keeping itself alive really is is is
like most fundamental to instinctual
goal directiveness and there's there
there can be other goals that complicate
the agent's Integrity like obsessions
and and like and how obsessions manifest
and so you know like we can think about
about oh right okay well as humans like
some of us are into sports some of us
are into video games or or or what have
you or you know I like to to you know
I'm I I I like to draw art art sketches
so there's certain things that are you
know there's certain other goals that
might not
necessarily um be directly or or or
maybe their
tertiary uh to to to the agent right
there's certain goals that might not
necessarily uh uh be be necessarily like
I don't I don't necessarily have to work
on artwork you know I could do I could F
do other things but like goal alignment
especially in terms of like goals that
are not
necessarily uh uh uh uh vital to to to
the agents Integrity like when we think
about like food water sleep and what
have you right those are fundamental
goals like there there's there's also
the complication of other goals that uh
kind of align with the interests of the
agent over time based on exposure
Dynamic when we think of nurture
Dynamics like you know like what what
stimuli ends up directing the agent to
develop these interests and obsessions
and what have you and now they they have
these goals that are that are aligned
with
like those obsessions or there or those
interests or what have you not to say
that interests are obsessions but um
just trying to come up with some
examples
there okay
um so I I kind of go uh I I I I uh in
this section over here talking about um
routine Behavior being integral to to
environment and agent based Dynamics I
kind of start off with like talking a
little bit about uh you know from from
the perspective of of of thinking about
physics and particle
interactions um and then getting to uh
of agent based behavior um
so we can think about how systems might
[Music]
um how how do how do how do how do
systems how do agents as as systems uh
maintain stability or acknowledging of
course the problem with cellular syence
and aging of systems like that system
degrade over
time um due to uh you know uh systems
degrade over time after prolonged
exposure toh to their environment and
and what have you and and those Dynamics
which
um
see which you know I don't think it's
necessarily necessary for me to talk
about entropy and what have you
but most systems you know uh degrade
from a a a a structured uh more
organized state to a more uh decomposed
chaotic State um which is
um
which which that that kind of connects
in a sense to to to problems with
cellular inessence like how as we get
older our fitness is more suboptimal but
even though our F Fitness is more
suboptimal as we get older we still try
to you know
optimize uh optimize the Integrity of of
of our agency by by engaging with with
our environment in ways that are are are
reinforcing reinforcement base even in
light of that suboptimality as opposed
to being counter
inuitive uh to
Fitness let's see
um and now um now resources I mentioned
resources uh re resources provide a VAR
A variation in which we can leverage our
fitness right so uh resources could be
like food that allow us to manage manol
load they could be uh certain aspects of
the of the environment that we can use
as like as tools to manipulate uh the
landscape of the environment um so
variational constraints in terms of
optimizing Fitness uh in line uh of of
our agency have to do with not how we uh
maintain ourselves but how we engage
with each other especially as a means to
to maintain uh our
fitness and there and and the
environment can not all not only
presents
resources that agents can utilize but
there might be barriers in the
environment there might be optimal there
in in a sense that there's obstacles
within the environment that provide
constraints in which the agent has has
has certain agency to
engage uh to engage with the environment
um more more intuitively or or you know
to to have better circumstances as
opposed to circumstances being being
worse uh based on certain resources not
being available to to the agent so that
could that could be an obstacle whe like
whether it's there certain resources
that that an agent was utilizing whether
it has to do with metabolic uh metabolic
uh Integrity more directly in terms of
food or whether there are there's
certain aspects of the environment that
can be utilized as as as like as tool
construction or means to communicate uh
with other agents right
um so so the environment um you know can
pose as a barrier if it can make it if
it if the
environment um makes it that it's more
difficult rather than more
intuitive uh for agents to uh
facilitate uh Integrity uh their Fitness
in terms of how they how agents engage
with each other and and how they
leverage their own
Fitness um intrinsically
um so we talked we I think I provide a
good overview of gold directed Behavior
now what I'm going to talk about
um so um that kind of so I'm going to
talk a bit about um this this aspect of
Regulation like trying provide more uh
Clarity on like okay well the the uh as
agents we're trying to
regulate uh we're trying to to regulate
an optimal means of
sustaining an optimal level of fitness
and and how does that work out right and
so
um maybe a number of you aren't familiar
with David Walbert but uh David walber
um talks
about uh This this term known as this
this
um this idea of guided random search
optimization so I'm gonna say that say
that again it's
a an anandra of words guided a guided
random search Behavior which has to do
um so if we think of Randomness we're
thinking about like this this act this
uh this uh um uniformity in
which uh uniformity in which certain
outcomes occur certain things can happen
right like that there's no uh there's no
uh there's no uh
prioritized there's no there's no
prioritizing of of of certain um ways
things might occur but there's
uniformity in which occurrences happen
and we could and so this
uniformity um especially understood in
in in in literature regarding prob
probability Theory
and uh denotes to what Randomness means
not it's not necessarily like a lot like
some people might think Randomness has
to do with spontaneity and what have you
and that might have to deal with
probably extremities of of of Randomness
per se that's not necessarily
random um but uh Randomness more so as
to do with with uniformity that there's
no there's no like selective favoritism
about how outcomes happen but that you
know there's there there's there's kind
of like this evening out of like how
outcomes and
circumstances uh happen in terms of
thinking about what
Randomness um implies
here and um David Walbert approached
this aspect of of thinking about um how
we um develop axiomatic systems
and um how we can think
about um you know when we think about
axioms we think about really us you know
how we how how we how
um how behaviors you know how can how
things are reduced um you know how far
can we reduce a a certain Behavior or
phenomena and
and when there are certain components
that can't be furthermore reduced but
can can you can use those components as
building blocks to
represent uh complications or
complexities of how
Behavior Uh how behavior Can can happen
with a system now now we're thinking
about axioms right so
um uh a good example of of of thinking
about ax is thinking about how
arithmetic happens right like how how we
can add or multiply numbers to get more
numbers and we get AR we have we have
inputs of numbers and we then we have an
output of numbers we have a range of
numbers so now we can think about when
we're when we're talking about agential
systems and we're thinking about
axiomatic properties of systems we're
really thinking about um you know how do
we reduce stimuli and Sensations
and generaliz
the way the way Ag gental Systems
generalize how to engage with stimuli
and um now
um I I just realized that I probably
didn't give a give the give give the
give give a give a an elaboration on
actions and priors as opposed to
perceptions regarding the P Cycle so let
me do that real quick before I go go
more into what is guided random search
behavior um which then leads to this
aspect of guided random search
optimization because
ultimately uh we as agal systems want to
optimize Fitness right um now okay so
perception has to do with uh perceiving
uh you know we're we you know as we're
engaging with stimulus and processing
Sensations we are for you know we're
perceiving uh we we are trying to figure
out okay um how do I engage with this
you know what what you know in terms of
top down you know we're talking about
top down here when when we're talking
about perception actions and priors um
although uh more simple agents uh it
could be argued that you know even
simpler agents have a means in which
they perceive act and anticipate even
though you know that their
capacity the capacity more simple agents
to engage with the environment is is is
is less complex because uh you know if
we're thinking about especially single
cell systems as compared to you know
humans we're these multi-agent systems
because we're we're composed of multiple
cells and
um we have these uh networks of neurons
and go cells that are facilitating
engagement and and communication with
different regions of other neural neural
and gu cellular networks that are
facilitating our capacity to perceive
act and anticipate so action has to do
with how we're responding to the
stimulus right so we're trying to
facilitate a
response uh to to to the stim to to to
how we're engaging with our environment
we're talking about action and then
prior or anticipation has to do with uh
ke like a history you know we keep track
of a of a history of our perceptions and
our actions and we then we try to
optimize based on that history we were
trying to
anticipate uh what H what what what
perceptions and actions ought to be
optimized going forward so on the one
hand with
perceptions uh uh you know we're we're
we're you know we're we're engaging with
an environment we're engaging with
stimulus when we're trying to figure out
okay how do I react to this how do I
respond to this and then next in line
once we once we once we have a
calculation in mind of like okay this is
going to be my action this is going to
be my response to the stimulus and now
when we're thinking about perceptions
actions and
priers um we again we we can think about
compositions thereof of of perceptions
actions and priors right you know we we
think about not only U you know even
even different modes of perceiving and
acting and and at times uh they you know
perception and actions are sort of
coupled you know based on like how
different regions of the brain are are
processing Sensations and
and you know once you process Sensations
you you have information to work with
and then you're prioritizing what
information matters after you prioritize
what Sensations
matter um now okay this guy did random
search now we're going back to to
axiomatic
systems um right we have this red we
have we have a we we we get to this
point where we try to
reduce uh Sensations right we try to to
decompose you know like especially when
we're processing Sensations and and
we're trying to um conduct this capacity
to perceive act and
anticipate ultimately we're we're trying
to come up with ways to to you know as
we're coming up with ways to predict
we're trying to uh you know we're trying
you know thinking about like that
example of arithmetic we're trying to to
you know reduce what the sensation to
what we try to
reduce to uh uh you know like Sensations
only reduce so much yet uh compositions
of those Sensations could start to build
a picture right like the bare reductions
of those Sensations might not make much
sense themselves but if we take the
compositions of those Sensations over
time and how they build up uh into
something that makes sense for us to you
know in terms of interpreting the
stimuli in terms of perceiving the
stimuli and then acting on the stimuli
after uh you know
facilitating uh okay how you know in the
p in in the perceiving of the stimuli
what's the best what's the most optimal
manner I can act on the stimuli and then
having a history of okay
well I in I perceived this stimuli this
way and I acted on it this way this is
what happened okay well the outcome
might have been good or might have not
been good so now I'm going to
anticipate how to perceive and act based
on the the outcome that may or may have
not been good and um in terms of of of
how my capacity to evaluate weight as
you know you know when we talk about uh
how um let's see um my capacity to
evaluate the the stimuli is reflective
of of like okay well uh I don't want to
call it trial and error here but this is
kind of how we're getting to the guided
random search aspect right that there
are there there's a combination of ways
that we take
the the
um that we take the
reductions of the sensations that build
into information right and then we that
become information this like this this
reduction of generalizations of
Sensations that become information uh
based on how we're prioritizing that due
to how we um select out perceptions and
actions and PRI that
optimize our fitness based on how we're
engaging with our environment um so like
um the guided aspect is uh prioritizing
what's working as opposed to what's not
working and the random aspect has to do
with okay well the sensations as we you
know we reduce the in when we
reduce the amalgamation of Sensations
that ultimately like I mentioned are
stimuli that we're being bombarded with
um though the aspects of those
Sensations really are
uniform um uh in in the sense that um
those you know when we don't really
prioritize those sens you know once
like
uh before those Sensations
become develop any relevancy as
information uh there's no
you know the environment doesn't really
necessarily dictate what sensation what
stimuli have priority the stimuli just
present themselves as
stimuli um to to to to our system and
then it's up to us based on how we
perceive and act and anticipate the
stimuli on how to how to it's up to us
to
prioritize
um that that stimuli which
which in uh in the Bare Bones aspects of
that stimuli outside of our judgment you
know outside of our own judgment which
involves perceiving acting and
anticipating is random because nature
doesn't really
care you know um nature doesn't really
care about you know reg you know
necessarily selectively regulating the
stimulus outside of the
agents uh like
like the environment the bare
environment doesn't care but the
agents among that environment you know
are going to engage with the environment
in a way that prioritizes stimulus and
and and guides the agents to engage with
each other in the environment right and
and in that sense the guided the guided
aspect is the prioritization the random
aspect is this uniformity that the the
bare bone stimulus presented in the
environment among agents there's no
there's you know until the
agents start to prioritize the
sensations as
information um there's really there's
really um Beyond there's really nothing
more than this uniformity of this you
know there's nothing there's nothing
really uh that that stands out about the
stimuli until the
agent uh starts to
uh make
selective uh uh
generalizations once once there once the
agent can notice patterns of stimulus
and those patterns would be information
and then the agent's going to try to
Prior prioritize those patterns so the
search Behavior now the search behavior
is recognizing the patterns and then fil
the filtering aspect of the patterns
right so like I mentioned the the guided
aspect has to do with the
prioritization the random aspect has to
do with okay well there's this
uniformity in which the stimulus is is
is provoking the agent to engage with
the
stimulus and then it's up to the agent
to kind of
categorize and and and and prioritize
the
stimulus and and reduce it to
information and then prioritize that
information based on like what the agent
think thinks is necessary to pay
attention to and so the the search
aspect is like this paying attent like
the intentional Dynamics involved with
this
prioritization
um so um now there's like I mentioned
there's constraints within the
environment that enable agents to to
facilitate uh perception action and
prior uh
Dynamics um in a way that would optimize
Fitness as opposed to
um deceive Fitness or or be
counterintuitive to
Fitness and now okay well when we talk
about
homeostasis uh again the environment's
not in a fixed uh static State Dynamic
uh agents aren't in a
fixed uh fixed state right everything
you know we have this complex adaptive
system that is the environment and we
also have this complex you know the
nature of
agenes of Agents uh invoking agency in
the environment or or trying to
compensate for what the
environment presents to agents as
resources or
obstacles
um homeostasis has to do with then um
how do agents sustain a minimum
viable U functional Integrity that is
that is that is crucial to Fitness to
allow the agent to continue to continue
to exist rather than than cease to exist
right so the so homeo so homeostatic
regulation um is going to have to do
with um and maybe some of you are
thinking of the free energy principle
um in this respect that um agents um
want to minimize cost but maximize on
opportunity to uh leverage optimizing
Fitness
um what least most agents want to do
that um very it's um I mean there there
are some aspects where where I think
we're agents that have the capacity to
annihilate themselves um which um I I
don't think uh
I think agents need a certain level of
complexity to make that decision from
the top down so so so in that respect
the top down Dynamics as opposed to the
bottom up Dynamics uh you know are are
are much more crucial to facilitating
the Integrity of an agent because you
know agents with enough sophisticated
agency like human beings can decide to
annihilate themselves which is
unfortunate but uh in most cases
it well I would say it's generally
unusual for for and we're seeing this in
the literature too that it's unusual but
it's
interesting um to uh you know where
circumstances arise where an agent makes
the evaluation that they can't really
optimize Fitness anymore than they have
so they so the most optimal the most
optimal decision for the agent is decide
is to decide for them to not EX exist
anymore um which is unfortunate um but
um this is not Al this also isn't
uniquely human either um you know other
other other there are other types of
Agents other animals out there you know
when we think again we're thinking about
agents as biological organisms here um
you know where an agent makes a decision
that that they can't really optimize
Fitness anymore and the the uh the the
circumstances in which the environment
provides any leverage of Integrity is
not really there so the most optimal
decision an agent can make is is to
annihilate itself but that that's I'm
not going to get really into that um but
I think it that's sort of an unfortunate
circumstance for an agent to find
themselves in and and this pertains to
probably um I you know more
sophisticated agents um as as I found in
in in the
literature
um
okay
see so we we went
over that we went over what stimulus
is and regarding again homeostasis that
has to you know this Builds on guided
random
search and the guided this being the
prioritization the randomness being the
uniformity in which
stimulus provokes the agent and presents
itself within the environment and we
acknowledge that stimulus is is really
um anything that in that that is
provoking the agent to perceive act or
anticipate anything that anything that H
that en that that provokes an agent to
perceive act or anticipate would be
considered a
stimulus
um and
prioritizing where was I
here being able to to prioritize
stimulus and for agents to minimize cost
to engage with their
environment uh and maintain
um um like a minimal F minimum VI
minimally viable functional Integrity
that that is crucial to Fitness this has
to deal with homeostatic regulation or
or
homeostasis this is what I call
homeostasis and the environment presents
means in which uh on the one hand can be
resourceful for agents to to regulate
their Fitness while on the other hand
the the environment might also present
obstacles that could be problematic to
regulating
Fitness so we could so okay we're going
to talk more about the mechan like the
mechanistic sort of a mechanistic
interpret
interpretability um explanation of of
the perception action and and prior
cycle or what I call the pap cycle
so uh a lot so a lot of you programmer
types and Engineering types are probably
familiar or hopefully are familiar with
the terms
sensor and actuator so uh on the one so
we could reduce all the all these
behaviors of agents perceiving and
acting on the environment as as well as
anticipating to be reduced to sensory
and actuator based Dynamics sensory
sensors being to sensory mechanisms like
uh
recognizing and and and um communicating
or signal you know recognizing and
signaling you know when we think about
how how neurons neuron and G's uh
cellular networks work together the
sensor capacities have to do with um
interpreting a signal and passing that
signal along to the right Networks then
deal with that signal and then you have
this coupled capacity of
sensory uh uh of sensory motor actions
involved that that deal with the
stimulus so actuators have to do with
acting so so so like having an action
towards the towards the stimulus so
actuators uh uh having this actuation
based
mechanism um has has to do with
responding to the stimulus while the
sensors or or the sensory capacities
signaling uh you know the signaling and
communication faculties that opt that
enable uh perceptions and actions and
anticipation Dynamics to be
optimized um you know certain networks
of neural uh um there are certain uh
there are neural and gal cellular
networks that that uh
interpret uh Sensations and
communicate uh what those those
Sensations are uh you know and they
signal to the to networks that deal with
the with acting and responding to the
stimulus right and and more so there's
uh it more there's this coupled capacity
of you have these coupled sensor
actuator based networks that um and
compositions thereof
that deal with handling stimulus and
Sensations and prioritizing the
sensations into information and so on
and so
forth and and the sensor and actuator
based mechanistic capacities you know
you know that that we reduce this you
you know we you know basically this is
this is this is a reduction of like okay
we have these neuro uh networks that
facilitate perception action
anticipation and we're trying to
optimize uh for metabolic costs and
facilitate cognitive
load uh that
um that leverages Fitness rather than
compr compromises Fitness
um over time um and and
and um in in the most realist I guess in
the most
uh pragmatic sense we think about this
minimum viable means in which uh we
facil in in which an agent
optimizes how it calibrates cost of
metabolic load for homeo for in with
regard to facilitating um
functional Integrity or homeostatic
regulation so hopefully that makes
sense so we could think of like when I
mentioned gold directed Behavior there's
this coordination of micro and macro
levels of how we as multi-agent systems
facilitate that right so like we think
from the bottom up we have
metabolic uh load handling or or
facilitation and from the top down we
have cognitive load
uh handling right we're thinking about
how cognitive load is mitigated due to
how metabolic load plays out as
cognitive load really is a subset of of
metabolic load because you need you need
you need metab metabolic costs to
facilitate everything that an agent does
like without being able to uh metabolize
the the agent just wouldn't exist it
wouldn't be able to continuously engage
with with its environment because it
needs resources like the agent needs uh
fundamentally one of one of the
fundamental
goal goals of the agent is to consume
resources whether that that's food water
you know we think about human behavior
we think about food water sleep um that
involves the consumption of metabolic
load and then uh of course other you
know you know other means like using
tools that um extensively enable us to
better leverage Fitness and how we
engage within our environment and other
agents is is also important but that's
more more secondary uh in terms like um
you know like tool use and and
augmentation and development
thereof
um is not as crucial as as maintaining
like uh metabolic load is in terms of of
of of food you know consumption of of
food and water being humans like to to
regulate that
fundamentally so we can think of like on
the macro level um cells represent you
know as multi-agent systems on the macro
level you know cells can represent or
whole organ systems and subsystems that
regulate from the bottom up as well as
the top down and then from the micro
level we think about how the individual
cells as individual unit agents engage
with each other because we ourselves
even though we are agents we are a whole
environment and ecosystem thereof of
Agents communicating with each other
that enables our own agency and our own
capacity to communicate the environment
in which we're embedded and so we have
agents embedded within us and then we
are also embedded within an environment
in which we have ageny and that is
constrained due to um the resources and
obstacles that the the
environment presents uh or the that that
ex the resources and obstacles that are
existent within the environment that
that we have constrained access
[Music]
to and then the
um there's also the um this is not
talked about that much in the liter but
there's also the Meso Level so we talk
about the micro level where we have the
individual unit agents within our
organism as a multi-agent system how how
those agents communicate with each other
but on the macro level we have the
different subsystems communicating with
each other and even on the macro level
we're thinking about the top- down
dynamics of regulating executive
function which also considers the macro
level about how networks of of of neuron
Gile cells are communic ating with each
other but we also have this Meso Level
and um this Meso Level we can think
about how selective uh more so when
we're thinking about the top down
regulation of agency we're thinking
about how different Sub sub regions of
our of our nervous system or our
executive functioning are regulating
agency our capacity to
continuously engage
with our environment in an optimal
fashion
so um so so thinking from the Meso Level
you think we can think about how
different regions regions of the brain
are are working together to evaluate
perceptions actions and priors like you
know like the prefrontal cortex uh the
reticular formation the the hippocampus
the amigdala like how are all these
subsystems
of of neural and gal cellular networks
facilitating
engagement um like we're going from the
more macro level of the of the central
nervous system to not necessarily the
micro level of the individual neurons
and and Gile cells but we're also
talking about how different how uh
different coupled
networks uh of these neuron cells of
these different regions are facilitating
lateral engagement with each other so I
think it's important also so for those
of you who don't necessarily have a
neuroscience
background um or psychology background
um uh
so no no one region of the like one like
all the regions of the brain first of
all are are communicating laterally in
the sense that they're communicating
they're they're engaging in parallel
processing stimuli and Sensations and
what have you and and information right
no one region is responsible like you
know the hippocampus uh doesn't doesn't
store and and you know even though like
the hippocampus is largely recognized as
the memory storage system the way it
stores and and references information it
needs to work with the amydala the phus
it has to work with the reticular
formation um it has to work with the
prefrontal
cortex um um so so no one region is
processing these Sensations at one point
or momentarily in time like they're you
know and we're in in an interesting way
we're going to get get to like um what
is in necessarily interesting about um
how our brains are structured and that's
not
necessarily uh a het it's not
necessarily hierarchical although it's
it's mostly hierarchical in the sense of
prioritizing stimulus and sensory
information but
um how uh how how that processing and
prioritizing builds out over time in
terms of how we as organ as these
biological organisms as multi as
agential multi-agent systems evolved um
is not just hierarchical but uh is
there's this other term that is less
familiar um so on on the on the one hand
we have this prioritization or or what
can be deemed as hierarchy of like o of
of
prioritizing uh of Sensations and and
and what have you on the other hand
there's the tuning aspect right like
sort of like as we're prioritizing and
selecting out uh stimuli loads as sens
and as Sensations and
information uh there's also uh this
aspect of sort of like tuning you know
like you know kind of like you know if
you think about like a like an audio
mixer or or a soundboard right you you
want to get the right you you kind of
want to you want to kind of Select out
the right uh
channels of how stimuli and Sensations
are being prioritized and this is known
as
heterarchical processing h t uh
heterarchical h
t archical so I'm not going to spell the
whole thing out but uh this is
heterarchical processing and and this
term is actually brought out in
um uh uh H H hubner and schulin
biological cognition paper which I
highly recommend uh and we're going to
talk a little bit about um this
uh this this u means of preserving
viability which
um which is pretty important to how
agents engage with each other to
optimize and leverage Fitness we're
going to talk about that
momentarily um but so there's this
there's this hierarchical capacity in
which the regions of our brain are
prioritizing stimulus right and and and
um in that prioritization and selecting
out the stimulus there's sort there's
this tuning coming there's there's kind
of like this channel
tuning uh mechanism right like trying to
just get the you know trying to trying
to prioritize the stimulus just the
right way involves like sort of like a
selective pressuring that's not
necessarily hierarchical but it's it's
sort it's
uh um it it it's also like um a little
bit more it's sort of like there's
degrees of freedom in which we we we try
to calibrate the channels in which those
Sensations uh are are being prioritized
as information and then then that
information is being selectively
prioritize uh so this is known as
heterarchical
processing um but largely speaking
what's happening is hierarchical because
that the actual
prioritization of
modalities that's hierarchical but that
can't happen without
calibrating uh the sensations and
information to be processed and this
calibrating aspect is
heterarchical um or like kind of like
you know think about a mixing board or a
sound board like like I don't know how
many people are are are into DJing or or
or producing music or what have you but
if you play with like a soundboard and
you're trying to get the right sound to
come out and you're and you're trying to
get the channel properties you're trying
to tune the channels and all that stuff
uh this is this is this is hyp you hyper
parameter hyper
param it's a tongue twister hyper
parameterized tuning processing of the
top down right like the idea of
parameterizing the sensations right like
when we're trying to facilitate the
parameterization of okay the stimuli
coming in and are perceiving and acting
on that
stimuli um the the param par par
parametric
tuning that that has to facilitate the
prioritization that is the heterarchical
processing that's
happening okay so
so there's there's um on the one hand
there's what what what's happening with
perception actions and prior and priers
is this introspective capacity of of
trying to
interpret uh stimuli and and then this
reactive
capacity uh this proprioceptive
capacity of aligning our perceptions and
actions uh with with how we anticipate
right so so our so so in terms of not
only our our um well this is in due part
to to the top down functioning but this
and this this really
calibrates uh our capacity to to not
only uh interpret but react and and and
and and react in a sense uh react to
stimuli uh in a sense of like uh uh of
predicting what's going to happen what
what's going to happen going forward uh
that would be Pro more more in the
proprioceptive sense of dealing with the
stimulus over time to optimize Fitness
so on the one hand there there's this
capacity in which uh um especially with
decision
making where uh we try and make sense of
what we ought to do how we how we how we
perceive and act on the stimulus then
our continued actions going forward in
time has to do with proprioceptive
capacities um so so this capacity to to
the means in which to to to to to to
regulate perception and actions based on
anticipations
um going into the future and and how how
how in terms of bodily functioning like
just just how I engage with the stimulus
in in a way that becomes more that feels
more
intuitive um this is appropriate
receptive capacity as opposed to more
introspective capacity of uh uh of of in
trying to interpret and understand the
stimulus and and in in and making a
decision that might be and making
decisions that might
reflect um uh what could happen in the
future then there is The Happening of
the future right and and the alignment
of that happening in the future that
that that it that it that um that is in
that is in line with anticipation has to
do with
proprioception
okay let's
see
um I don't want to speak too conf
confidently about about the main regions
of the brain
coordinating uh coordinating our
capacity of perception actions and
priors but I I'll I'll I I'll I'll bring
some some key some regions that have
caught my eye um there's a bit of
contention in terms of what are the key
regions that are are responsible for our
capacity to perceive act and
anticipate uh the most evolved capacity
uh that really sets humans apart uh has
to do with the prefrontal cortex so that
that deals a lot with
planning and and and perception that
there a lot of the modalities in which
planning in terms of perception and gold
directedness has to do with the
prefrontal
cortex um the anterior CeX has more to
do with the sensory motor
functioning um now um less what's less
talked about in the literature um is the
role of the reticular formation so
that's your brain stem so the reticular
formation has to do with autonomic
arousal so so this like the capacity to
even uh
uh uh engage with Sensations at all uh
has to do with the reticular formation
and in particular what I uh my favorite
uh part of the brain um is the locus
corus or also known as the the LC NE
system or the
the the what regulates
norepinephrine um so so so autonomic
arousal is pretty important because what
without it like we're we're we're not
really engaging you know
um I mean there's no means for stimulus
to to to be interpreted and and
facilitated throughout the uh the brain
so so so the norepinephrine system is is
allowing us to interpret this the
stimulus and guide that interpretation
in terms of signaling uh all these all
the different primary primary regions of
the brain uh that are responsible for
perception action and anticipation and
now what I like to call The neuromorphic
Interchange is the limic system now the
lyic system is
basically uh basically the region that
encompasses like basic uh the the key
regions of executive functioning so
thinking about memory retrieval
motions um plan angle directedness um
sensory motor processing so the
prefrontal cortex at least most most of
the prefrontal
cortex uh or the Neo cortex layer uh the
hippocampus the amydala the you know all
all those all those really important
regions that are are are important for
are for executive functioning are Guided
by the the limic system right uh well
they're
connected together by the limic system
like they they facilitate each other's
capacity due to um being housed into
this interchange that facilitates their
engagement which I call the limic
system and uh let see
all right going to the next
section Sensations are fundamental to
perception action and
anticipation I think I covered most of
this so this idea of generalizations of
Sensations
um is this feeding of
stimulus be uh as inputs into into
multiple our multimodal way of of
engaging with the
stimulus uh has to do with this General
of Sensations in which that the stimulus
is fed into the system initially and
this is this is a this is the
visceral uh this is this is the visceral
of the stimul the
viscerality I guess viscerality is the
right word so the means of internalizing
the stimulus is this generalization of
the stimulus itself right which is
visceral in natural right like think
about like when we think about visceral
like think about how blood flow is just
naturally happening like throughout your
body or or certain like like even
metabolic uh metabolic processing um
when we think about uh
the
uh uh the
um glycolysis and and all these
different behaviors that happen that
that regulate metabolic processing uh
cellular respiration right all like
stuff that's just constantly happening
that that that
regulates metabolic
load uh this like that's generally Prett
you know that that that um like like
these behaviors that that aren't really
particularly that interesting that that
correlate uh directly to to our
executive top down functioning this can
be recognized as visceral processing
like uh you know
uh U like stimulus that that isn't that
that's just constantly happening or or
this
processing this this load processing
that's constantly happening that that's
not that interesting but it it's it's
kind of fundamental to like how how our
continuous engagement with the
environment as as as agential systems is
regulated that's what we can denote as
um visceral processing
and this internalization of of of
stimulus uh with respect to
environmental constraints of
course um has to do with um you know
we're we're filtering the noise in this
generalization of Sensations like this
this capacity of General uh of filtering
the noise into becoming um a means in
which we can make sense of it um so we
prioritize that noises
information and that eventually allows
us to anticipate you know how should we
perceive and act accordingly to the
stimulus being presented to
us and then we have these recollection
of experiences because we're able to
anticipate based off of our history of
perceiving and acting to stimuli
now now here's where things get
interesting because I'm about to talk
about system one and system two uh
coupled with the Rider and the Elephant
uh so uh system one and system two uh
refers to Daniel
conoman uh in uh where system one has to
do with
uh uh decisions and be and ways of act
engaging with our environment uh from a
top down level executive functioning
level which is which is more automatic
and less involved while system two has
to do with um non-trivial or problem
solving circumstances which take more
effort
so now that has to do with with with
with
reasoning and and how we optimize
engagement with our
environment uh now um we couple this
Capac
with Jonathan hates the Rider and the
elephant and the reason why uh this
isn't this is well this is this is of
interest is um especially with system 2
processing we use emotional veilance
processing um or emotions these these
feelings the feelings we get from from
the general generalization of the
sensations that we we have as these
embod
um uh as these embodied beings but like
as AG gental Systems our engagement is
embodied right this this this capacity
to generalize
Sensations um as agents is is embodied
which this is what really separates us
from from classical machines or just
just you know these closed loop
circuits um and I would argue
additionally that um the way that we
perceive act and anticipate is not
necessarily A a closed loop um it uh it
it's sort it's sort of like an open
system but it's not uh it's like a
bounded open
system um we we'll we'll get into that a
little bit soon um now
um what's interesting about uh so
talking about the rider and yelf and I
need to elaborate on that so system one
system two system one is like kind of
automatic doesn't take too much effort
to make a decision and and and and and
system to it takes a little bit of
effort it's
non-trivial uh now the Rider and the
Elephant the rider is like the voice of
reason while the elephant is like the
experiencing like of the of the the
feeling States right so one can only
imagine an elephant going rampant in the
village right like the rider doesn't
have a good grip of the of the elant the
elephant just go crazy um so I so I
couple this idea of the Rider and the
elephant with system one system two
because um especially with system
two it takes some it takes some uh you
need a way you need a a a non-classical
logical uh system reduction way to uh
take
uh uh feeling States emotion States in
in where uh decisions are not are not
trivial or or they're not like there
these non there's these nonlinear
non-trivial circumstances in which we
have to make decisions or make
predictions or or you know like how we
engage with stimulus and how we try to
make make anticipations of how should we
perceive an act going forward into
especially the distant future right that
it could be a big deal in terms of
leveraging
Fitness so
um so so this
uh so so we so what we so what happens
here where decision making is not so
intuitive is we can try and figure out a
way to have decision weights as criteria
to evaluate decisions where there there
is some uncertainty involved where we're
not certain how things are going to pan
out and we have to
anticipate as agents like how how should
we engage optimally with our environment
so
emotions uh play a role uh in this
capacity where where decision- making is
non-trivial
nonlinear um and um there's this
generalization of feeling States right
when we when we're talking about
generalization of
Sensations uh so first we have to
consider that raw Sensations have to be
process by specialized regions which of
of our executive
functioning uh that deal with memory
consolidation uh regarding optimizing
priors as well as um emotional veilance
processing so effective processing uh is
involved here um so since so what
happens is Sensations become these
streams of information that are
comprehensible for modes of reasoning
and and emotion balance waiting that
can optim more optimally guide
perceptions and actions on
PRS um now
um what can be understood as emotions uh
then would be generaliz this this veence
weight this emotional veillance waiting
on generalized feeling states that um is
is separate but necessarily uh is
separate but necessary for optimizing
rationale and according accordance to
decision-making so we have this
interwovenness of reasoning and emotions
or or feelings right espe and and
emotions kind of um uh provide a a means
to weigh decisions that are especially
more difficult
where it's not
obvious uh what we how we should
anticipate uh what's going to happen in
the future and and just how to guide uh
our our
Behavior Uh especially in moments of
uncertainty
um and uh it could be argued that
consolidation of mem memories would be
largely
compromised if emotions did not provide
emphasis on how memories are referenced
in the first place because you need a
reference pointer and that's what the
these emotions themselves like these
emotion weights themselves function as
like a a reference a point of
reference uh in how we rationalize our
our our be our our perceptions and
actions uh based on how we anticipate
so in accordance to that if we can't uh
if memories cannot be properly
referenced on weigh decisions then how
how how can our how can we optimize
perception and action according to
minimizing uh compromising Fitness right
uh that that would that's a that's quite
an existential question like if we
didn't we weren't capable of emotions on
some level like how would we carry
Baseline decisions that allow us to
effectively anticipate what what do we
do next B based on our environmental
circumstances right
um maybe that's not super intuitive but
to me that that kind of is
um so we talked bit we talked about
system one system two and the Rider and
the Elephant we talked a bit about
hierarchical and process hierarchical
and heterarchical uh processing so again
hierarch has to do with
prioritizing stimulus and
information and heterarchy has to do
with the like how we parameterize it how
we select it out in in the in
association with the with the
prioritization so they're kind of
coupled together but of course
priority uh is what the priority is what
matters even though we select out
certain perceptions and actions in
accordance to how we're
optimizing our
engagement and and hopefully I
elaborated that clearly but um I could
always go back to that a little bit
later if there's questions about that uh
let's see relativistic I'm going to skip
this
section four regions all right
so this is this is uh probably one of my
favorite parts of the paper
uh right here is talking about reality
as an interface or or reality is an
interface um and uh this is kind of this
was this gained a lot of popularity in
Don Hoffman's collaborative paper with
um uh with Chris fields and chatan Pros
um especially elaborating on like the
boundary you know we're talking about
perceiving and acting and how agents are
you know agents have a boundary within
the environment they're engaging with
right but even more interesting is that
I make the case 4 is that agents
themselves are existentially embedded
within the environment that they're
engaged in and uh this can argue I would
say arguably this could extend to
artificial artificial agents that they
rely on some on resource leverage within
the environment that they're engaged in
for them to continue to exist or or
function
right and uh now reality as an interface
uh we think about this this uh you know
this phenomenal capacity for us to
engage with stimuli and and and and and
react to it right um and and this can
this can like very deeply uh you can
really argue reality as an interface
like deep down P you know past the fact
of of organisms and talking about
physics and and and just how
SpaceTime uh that the the the the
fabrication of SpaceTime maintains
itself is that uh particles are
interacting with each other in some
capacity even though they don't
necessarily have any agency uh but most
importantly we as agents are constantly
engaging with each other we're
constantly interacting with each other
so to speak in the phenomenal sense so
that really has to to deal with reality
as an interface and extensive and
building on that we talk I I mentioned
axiomatic systems uh sort of as the
reduction uh you know we we we're we're
we decompose
Sensations uh reductively axiomatically
and and we can relate that to David
walbert's argument uh of talking about
uh okay well we we base a lot of our we
base our reasoning on mathematics
mathematics is based on axiomatic uh
constructions of
systems um and we have base components
that allow us to uh construct Pro uh to
elaborate on properties of of systems or
construct systems uh compositionally in
a number of ways uh based
on uh like like base base uh like
Baseline uh rules like for instance
considering the rules of arithmetic
right
um let's see is there certain things
that I
should we talked a bit about guided
random search
um so this idea of abstract reasoning is
rooted axiomatically because making
decisions involves uh involves again
trying to make sense of the sensations
that we're trying to generalize and
we're trying to prioritize those
Sensations as information and then we
try and prioritize that
information
um to make sense of the world around us
in which we're constantly interfacing
and engaging with
so um now we uh come to an interesting
dilemma of uh when we deal with this
understanding of of okay well we're
constantly engaging with the world
around us and we can
decompose uh our engagement um
axiomatically so to speak especially
when we uh try to reduce Sensations and
um we we try and figure figure out how
to filter those Sensations into
information and prioritize that
information based on how we prioritize
Sensations as information then we're
prioritizing the
information um okay
well in mathematics there's uh this this
this this hole um that is brought about
uh due to Kurt girdles incomplete
uh
theorems um not really going to get in
that into that but uh what really should
be
um what what what should be uh the moral
of the story is uh that uh the lack of
consistency
um in how we construct you know in the
sense of how how gerle uses uh uh uh
uses uh the ax uses the axioms of
arithmetic as an example and trying to
uh map those axioms to how we construct
the natural numbers um there's uh
there's
inconsistencies uh that he
presents um in that
um and I guess this this more so uh in
you know this sort of Pro provides an
insight into uh the inconsistency in how
we generalize Sensations as information
and then we try and generalize
information and try and have a
consistent interpretation of reality
which um in the
illusionists which in The Illusionist
sense uh you could argue that we never
have a true represent ation of reality
but um enough of us can come to an
agreement on some representation on of
reality based on on how we formally rep
uh uh how we formally rep uh uh
represent uh how we formally present
models of the world around us so in
terms of making predictions about how
certain of aspects of reality Works how
certain aspects of of the environment
like how how how do we generalize uh
ways in which we can engage with the
environment not for ourselves but to
facilitate cooperation with other agents
right like if there's there are means in
which we can collectively come to some
agreement that makes sense in the moment
and then there's a better way to make
sense of it in the future uh more so The
Illusionist aspect is that we're not
going to you know we would be deluding
ourselves elves if we truly thought like
understood reality for what it is rather
than really uh
generalizing uh certain features of it
that uh pertain to optimizing Fitness
and our survivability and our engagement
so ultimately we're we're
exploring our environment and we're and
we're just trying to uh optimize our
Fitness with respect to how we engage
with each other and and ourselves within
the
environment
um and uh the inconsistence the
inconsistency is is the general the
generalizations that we make that um
become replaced with better models in
the future so that's not
necessarily
uh that's not
necessarily uh
the same exact reasoning that girdle
that Kurt girdle makes saying well we
have this inconsistency of
mapping the uh properties of of
arithmetic in which we can we can
compose certain uh systems with
arithmetic uh and map that to natural
numbers in which we for which we assign
each composition that we come up with
using
arithmetic uh as uh some um iteration
within the natural numbers and then we
come to some property that says that uh
this property disproves that this prop
um this property shows that um this
isn't
true uh
well
uh yeah you you come to you come to a
property uh that that that shows
inconsistency say saying okay well uh
this this isn't
true
uh
uh how did it
go yeah basically you bump into to to a
problem where you eventually uh
formalize a a condition that is a
contradiction saying that
uh uh
that uh that that that is that uh
that it's escaping me right now but
essentially you you bump into a
formalization of a contradiction within
trying to uh compose conditions that are
consistent with with the axum aums of of
arithmetic but anyway that's kind of
outside of the that that's outside of
the scope of this
presentation the the whole means of like
the whole point about inconsistency is
that we're constantly
generalizing how we're engaging with the
world around
us uh as
agents uh okay you're right uh so
like basically what girl came up with a
with a property with with with with with
a condition that said uh like this this
card proves that uh that that this that
that you know like this this condition
proves that it's false otherwise it's
true right so like you have a condition
that proves that something is not untrue
but it it it but it's also true that
it's not true that that's the
contradiction in a nutshell um that's
not exactly how he phrased it but I'm
like talking off the top of my head um
but you basically arrive at a
contradiction
um and and kind of sort of uh relating
that back to how we generalize
Sensations and information is we never
have a completely consistent picture of
reality um especially how we engage with
it and we're constantly reform re
reformulating how we interpret our
reality for what it
is and and that itself is the illusion
not that re reality isn't an illusion
but our understanding of reality is
elusive because we're constantly
generalizing um what reality really
means I think we're ready to talk about
preservation of
viability okay so this is where uh and I
spend a lot of time in this paper
talking about interagent Dynamics in
terms of like how cooperation is
essential for how we uh as as how we
even got to Modern civilization as as
humans like if we didn't cooperate well
enough together we just wouldn't have
gotten you know we wouldn't have zoom
calls we wouldn't have gotten to where
we are if there was not some sufficient
means in which we we cooperated with
each other effectively as sufficiently
large
groups of
humans um and this goes back to this
preservation of viability which really
has to
do uh with how um we consider tradeoffs
in engaging with our
environment while also we consider how
uh we engage with each other and
recognize and have this
awareness uh of our own degrees of
autonomy with respect to other other
humans as agents but uh we aren't the
only agents that exists within the
environment there are other agents that
aren't humans that don't have the
degrees of autonomy that humans have and
we ought to acknowledge their existence
as well and try to acknowledge the
tradeoffs in optimizing how we engage
with the environment and other agents
that aren't humans uh that I kind of
call lesser agents
um that they don't necessarily have the
the the same degree of autonomy to
engage uh with the environment around
them and I'm going to get into that in a
moment um but really there's this
there's this idea of this uh optimal e
and flow of guiding our priors with
which is not limit to limited to
individual Fitness of us individually
but also how we engage with each other
so there's this there's this idea of
interagent
coordination uh that ought to be
facilitated and and we could think about
this in a diplomatic sense of like how
we engage with each other
[Music]
um and and ultimately this increases the
well-being uh of of each other and
ourselves and our overall odds of
survival and acknowledging that that you
know uh the Dynamics of modern society
itself uh where we fluidly communicate
with each other through evolution of
language technology and bartering would
not be possible if we did not rely so
much on how we coordinate and cooperate
with each other is that that's critical
to just how we got to where we are as
human
civilization
um and engagement uh with each other not
only increases our chances to optimize
Fitness but it
enables uh our capacity to further
develop uh our awareness and means of
engaging with our environment in a way
that can become more optimized over time
at scale right because more and more of
us exists we have to think about scaling
uh problems with scaling and and how we
collectively engage with each
other and consider perception and
actions of others not just our own uh
perception and actions and how we
anticipate but as as collectively how
how we how we all coordinate and
cooperate in such a in such a fashion to
to to facilitate
that um
so so this is there's this idea of
co-inhabitants and it's not just humans
that exist on this planet that but
there's other organisms that uh do not
have the degree of autonomy that we of
agency we have but they serve functional
role within the ecosystem for us to
exist so I'm talking about all kinds of
life like plant life uh you know uh not
just animals but plants fungi molds like
uh insects if it wasn't for you know the
existence of pollinators and and all
these different species of organisms if
they didn't exist we wouldn't exist so
we have to take we have to
acknowledge that um you know it it you
know this that we co-inhabit um and
actually some literature that came out
recently come comes up with this term Co
co-evolution that we co-evolved with the
with I don't use the term biosphere uh
in my work other than the abstract but
we co-evolved with all these species
that we co-inhabit the environment with
and we're all
embedded uh we're all essentially
embedded within this this ecosystem that
we
co-inhabit and so I think there should
be more awareness brought to that front
in terms with how you know there there's
so much there's such an issue with human
conflict and just you know what I see as
like this this uh uh this bias of not
really recognizing at scale that we
ought to do more to to to work together
and symbiotically coexist with our
environment uh we we ought to hold
ourselves more accountable as a species
because we have this we have this level
we have such degrees of agency in a
awareness that
uh that gives us the that allows us
enables the potential for how we can
cooperate and where that can lead us uh
I mean it got modern it got humans to
Modern civilization which I think is
absolutely phenomenal um and we're going
to get a little bit into that
um but um before I get into that I want
to talk a little bit
about uh uncertainty um so this kind of
goes back to uh leverage and guided
random
search um where um there are moments
with regarding to calibrating our
perceptions with regard to next actions
that we take in accordance to the Past
and Present Moment uh what could unravel
in the future regarding optimizing our
priors especially when we're facing
moments of uncertainty right so um this
ha this this has to do with
complications that happen with
regulating uh system 2
Dynamics um and uh this uh when regards
to non-triviality nonlinear evaluations
of
decisions um and uh this can complicate
how we reason about the world around us
and regulate our emotions and
um uh and how we can persistently act
effectively in a re in a way that's
reinforcing our fitness so a persistent
uncertainty
uh that uh persistent uncertainty with
respect to conducting the capacity to
perceive and and act effectively can
hinder the efficiency in leveraging and
reinforcement learning Behavior making
us more immediately prone to acting
maladaptively eror prone signaling of
sterilizations of Sensations becomes
more prominent in the face of
uncertainty uh which can end up
deceiving our our senses instead of
being able to effectively optimize our
priors in the face of circumstance so on
the one
hand uh dealing with uncertainty uh
involves novelty exploration where we
try to improvise and figure out ways to
uh to how we can calibrate our
perceptions and our actions with respect
to optimizing our
priors uh and
then and and that has to do with with
how we recall like how how we we're
engaging with our environment in the
past right we talk a lot about like
anticipation with respect to
perceiving and acting and and uh novelty
really um you know it's not just the
improvisation it's kind of being
clever and um trying to experiment with
ways to optimize
Fitness in the face of
uncertainty
um and this can be this can be leveraged
in the short term as well as the
longterm
um where uh novelty can be
leveraged by uh considering how we
recall experiences in dealing with
circumstances that are either out of the
ordinary or just by happen stance making
a recollection from some point in the
distant or not so distant past relative
to perception that may Aid in
improvising against optimizing priors
and uh we can consider this uh
uh an aha moment like oh I figured out
what to do um so in terms of novelty
exploration and you know finding
yourself dealing with
uncertainty um that that's one aspect of
handling uncertainty another aspect of
uncertainty is just being is
unfamiliarity um like an agent being
unfamiliar with
circumstances uh they're going just
going to be have this uh sense of
unfamiliarity of what to do and maybe
other agents could help facilitate that
that that have experience in dealing
with those circumstances that that in
accordance can help you know with
cooperation can help the agent optimize
uh those moments of uncertainty by
becoming familiar or at least developing
that familiarity themselves uh which
might be prompted by novelty
exploration um
now now here so there's there's there's
a couple uh there's two primary modes uh
there's two there's
uh how do I say this
see okay so
on the one hand um there can be a means
in which uh there's problems
interpreting uh what we can do from
perceptive uh point of
view um that deals with
interpretation
uh and this is this has to do with um
now when we can problems with
uncertainty this is sort of kind of like
the halting I would I kind of call it
the halting problem of agency where an
agent doesn't quite know what to do
until they figure it out or maybe they
don't figure it out and you know that
kind of Dooms the agent but um
so on from an interpretive point of
view
um we can consider that uh there's
problems with considering what decision
to make in terms of
uh uh the determinable SE the
determinable sequence of actions in line
with an agent capacity to perceive their
surroundings considering contextual
variation of intrinsic and extrinsic
value
um so that has to do with an
interpretation being uh the problem of
uh uh uh of uh aligning that that aligns
with uncertainty that there's there the
agent is having a problem interpreting
what to do uh on the other
hand uh there is this
um so interpretation has to do with
problems with the agent perceptively
reflecting on their priors Moment by
moment to understand what they ought to
do to
resolve problems with optimizing Fitness
on the other hand there's problems with
functional capacities of dealing with
uncertainty where the actions determined
where the actions determined and
executed upon Moment by moment that fall
in line with perception in alignment
with priors
um there that there's a problem with
um there's a problem with actions being
selectively and sequentially carried
out with regard to context by moment so
on the one hand uh there uh uh
uncertainty could be a problem with
inter with perception on the other hand
uh uh uncertainty can also be a problem
of functional capacities in terms of
like not just perception but also like
how the Asian ought to act uh with
respect to the the circumstances they're
dealing with uh and selectively carrying
out certain sequences of actions Moment
by moment where they're kind of stuck
trying to trying to carry out uh the
action as opposed to uh making a
decision on on on on what how to
interpret the circumstances they're in
on the other hand um you know they also
have problems with like acting on on the
circumstances they're in as
well uh what else should I is there
something interesting to say on
this so I'm not going to I mention that
uh that this is like the halting problem
in terms of uh um you know um having
difficulty perceiving or acting uh for
the agent that compromises their Fitness
um the traditional sense of the halting
problem is when uh there's problems
where you condition an
algorithm uh on certain inputs and and
um you don't feed any information for
the uh into a system for an Al algorithm
to evaluate it so it just Waits uh for
inputs to come in or or rather it just
hangs there and it does and you know the
system doesn't do anything it just is
just waiting to
engage uh with a user on this hand um uh
the halting problem as I condone it to
be is problem with dealing with
uncertainty where the agent just has
problems
perceiving understanding uh you know
know developing an understanding of of
how to make sense of the circumstances
they're in uh in an interpretive point
of view on the other hand the agent also
can have difficulty uh
with under uh with uh action like like
uh with with with with carrying out how
they go about their circumstances
right so hopefully that that makes sense
comp
complications regarding
uncertainty
see right so I so not only uh is
uncertainty uh deals with unfamiliarity
where the agent is Con constrained to
exploring novelty or novelty explor
exploration but
also
um that U the agent might just not be
familiar with what to do and they just
need to figure out what to do and that
not that might not necessarily be novel
for all the agents that are that have
dealt with that circumstance but it
could be just novel for for the agent
dealing with that circumstance and on on
the one hand if they cooperate with
another agent that understands what to
do and that agent communicates what to
do and that resolves that
misunderstanding or um maybe sort of a
novelty exploration sense the agent
figures out themselves so I guess you
can call it a novelty exploration case
uh in that sense and um this this has to
do with um uh you know these moments of
uncertainty deal with error proness and
compromise of system 2 Dynamics
right so
let's
see and uh we and uncertainty itself uh
really arises from moments of ambiguity
where where information does not present
enough Clarity for the
agent uh to perceive and act effectively
in alignment with priors to optimize
Fitness
um and I and I do kind of compare how
that differs between computers like how
comp you know comput you know Computing
systems that we're familiar with is
different um I'm not going to get too
into that
um so unlike uh let's
see okay perceptions actions and
alignment of priors become vulnerable to
risk-taking Behavior with respect to
facing ambiguity as behavioral Dynamics
become a gamble on Fitness of the agent
in question risk-taking behavior however
is not necessarily maladaptive in its
nature but is prone to compromise the
agent's Fitness in which the the risks
taken May likely become
maladaptive uh given complications that
happen with regulating rationale
capacities and emotion through put under
moments of ambiguity most especially for
us uh human organisms become vulnerable
to experience what is commonly known as
anxiety uh so now I'm going to talk
about anxiety I'm going talk little real
quick about anxiety as a complication of
ambiguity and um that really has to be
that that's really worrying about what's
going to happen in the future
um largely
um and being prepared to deal with those
circumstances so when an agent is is in
this dilemma of what it can
do regarding future circumstances
um then it's in in it's dealing with uh
what I like to call anxiety um that
would be some uh
anxiety let's see here
um anxiety Then would would be some
level of Behavioral fixation which
permeates due to lingering uncertainty
in calibrating perceptions and
conducting appropriate next actions this
permeation ultimately presents self as
layers of thought-based as well as
compulsion based complexes that
complicate perception with respect to
generalizing next actions and aligning
priors um given that anxiety is largely
psychological the degrees of anxiety
permeation are primarily due to nurture
Dynamics where we consider constraints
with regard to environmental exposure
that can hinder adaptation most
especially with regard to trauma
response uh anx and so hypervigilance is
also uh complicates anxiety or rather
over sensitivity in processing stimuli
as well as overreactivity to responding
to stimuli which can be marginally
rooted from physiological constraints
hypervigilance can also arise due to
behavioral fixations arising from
complications and nurture
Dynamics uh more concisely
hypervigilance presents itself as
complex behaviors that enable our human
organism to act on alert with regard to
optimizing our perceptions actions and
aligning priors moments of
hypervigilance can be useful when
circumstances align well with Fitness
however hypervigilance May pose to be
maladaptive when it becomes
compromised um most especially due to
problems with upbringing or overexposure
to certain environmental stimuli
triggers
so now we're going to kind of get
into uh hyperarousal as opposed to
hypoarousal so sensory processing
complications that pose problems in
calibrating perception are largely due
to moments of noise filtering from
generalizations of fil of Sensations
being over undercompensated so this
overcompensation has to do with
hypervigilance while this under comp
compensation has to do with hypo
vigilance
or or hyp hyper hyperarousal as opposed
to hypoarousal
and uh overcompensation of of sensory
processing should however not be
confused to be equivalent to some form
of anxious Behavior but rather that
moments of hyperarousal potentially
complicates permeation the permeation of
how anxiety takes form and persists
and all
right risk-taking Behavior with respect
to
uncertainty so
uh see so marginal risk is always
associated with metabolic load demands
and cognitive load demands um there's
always some some risk associated with
just engaging with with our with
environment
and uh you know trying to prioritize
resources and dealing with
obstacles um that that you know
inevitably comes you know even risks
that we're unaware of that we're
unconscious of um and also there's you
know just given problems with cellular
inessence and aging and becoming more
suboptimally fit in the over time and
you know also presents risks uh
inevitably
right
uh so so here's a interesting uh bit I
want to bring up regarding uh
risk-taking there's a fine line between
risk-taking Behavior associated with
associated with uncertainty and
risk-taking behavior due to intentional
intentionally maladaptive Behavior given
that we associate risk-taking with
perceptions and action based gambling on
Fitness cognitive biasing is involved
with evaluating these gambl
fundamentally speaking unless there is
intention behind a particular agent
deceiving itself we
consider such Behavior to be risk
associated with acting in accordance to
uncertainty with respect to the agent in
question clearly risk is associated with
an agent's intentions be it
self-deceptive or otherwise if there is
marginal compromise to be considered in
the case of optimizing Fitness in some
fashion regardless risk is
inevitable to the well-being of Agents
as marginal compromise to Fitness not
only is pertinent based on Executive
functioning Dynamics in system one
system to processes but even metabolic
load processing Dynamics from bottom up
that are not necessarily directly
associated with executive functioning
from the top
down and this is the second to last
section I have to go over uh
reinforcement learning
see what I can pick out of
here this is really getting more really
into reinforcement learning with regard
to agency
um so
um deterrence uh is something I I
realized didn't really talk about
deterrence
at least U the current
mechanisms
so this is
interesting uh given the the whole point
of reinforcement learning behavior is to
leverage perceptions actions and prior
to optimize Fitness uh a rather
interesting expectation one ought to
conjure is that reinforcement has much
to do with deterrence from perceiving
acting and anticipating
maladaptively um deterrence however
ultimately is not the goal of
reinforcement learning based Behavior
but rather some reinforcement learning
based behaviors provide mechanism that
mechanisms of deterrence but not
all most especially if a habitual
behavior that was once reinforcement
based transitions into maladaptive
Behavior due to environmental
constraints impacting the Dynamics of an
organ of an agine in question and such
Behavior Uh cannot provide a mode of
deterrence clearly on the other hand
there can also exist reinforc learning
based behaviors that act as modes of
deterrence that become ineffective and
thus transition to maladaptive Behavior
being able to align perceptions and
actions with regard to precautionary
constraints that alert the agent in
question with regard to priors
effectively demonstrates a mode of
deterrence okay so here's something
interesting uh about deterrence
um and then um I might go a little bit
over language and how that's important
to uh
how uh we engage with each other uh in a
Cooperative fashion that got got us as
humans to where we are um but um so just
want to close off the tance
here um
see
okay yeah I'm going to try and wrap up
this this this whole section um right
certain reinforcement learning based
behaviors may not have precautionary
constraints aligned to them although May
momentarily leverage Fitness due to
opportunities in which the agent in
question does not incur Fitness
penalties with regard to assess
metabolic and functional risk that
compromise overall Integrity
additionally while agents may be aware
of modes of deterrence they they may be
intentionally oblivious to them with
regard to agents being intentionally
self-deceptive towards modes of
deterrence the purpose of doing so
involves Fitness trade-offs which in
large part not only encourages marginal
risk associated with Fitness penalties
over time but also tends to be optimized
with regard to anticipating a trade-off
in which the agent in question is
convinced will pay off in the short term
or long term where things go AR with
such self-deception and other means of
self-deception varies with regard to the
magnitude of maladaptive Behavior being
enacted by the agent in question a
rather paradoxical remark can be made
regarding deterrence perhaps there are
degrees of deterrence associated with
reinforcement learning based behaviors
as associated with fundamental uh the
fundamental alignment of perceptions
actions and priers such fundamental
alignment is variable in terms of
navigating our environment with respect
to what we consider a fitness landscape
of associated risks and precautionary
constraints to consider these Associated
risks and precautionary precautionary
constraints enabled an agent in question
to leverage optimizing Fitness and
attentively Rec recognizing obstacles
and aspects of the environment to be war
of in order to furthermore avoid
incurred Fitness penalties that could
that would be otherwise obvious to the
agent in
question um so
the rest of this
section um talks about uh interagent
cooperation based
Dynamics uh and then the other section
that I completed uh goes over Mal
adaptive learning Behavior so um I
talked a bit about uh cooperation of
agents and how that's important so what
separates us as humans uh from
uh any other agents that exist is just
our capacity to to utilize and develop
language to a point where we can take
information and and have what we could
take that information and turn it into
generalized knowledge us using language
to uh we can take language and
information and make
associations that stay consistent over a
prolonged period of time
with how we as humans engage with each
other and and are able to leverage uh
the uh resources and constraints of our
environment and and that impacts uh like
how we develop social structures and and
just this this this uh capacity of
cohesiveness and and and how we utilize
language to augment our capacities to
better optimally engage with our
environment and
furthermore
uh uh uh abstract the world around us
and
make uh generalizations of information
and generalize
knowledge
um just get to
it
um the the the capacity to take an
incorporated sophistic ated Lang
structured language
system and map that to
Concepts uh using language um becomes
generalized
knowledge um and this is this is really
what separates us from other agents and
and how we got to where we
are um and so we can think of like M
medic adaptation capacities emphasized
through Celia Hayes work on imitation
learning and medic cognition Dynamics
and more interestingly we can also uh
consider uh France SWAT Chet's uh
conceptualization of intelligence
generalization on how we make
generalizations about our perceptions
and actions and and anticipate our
environment but in so in in a collective
fashion utilizing this capacity of
structured of of of language and how
we're able to like furthermore augment
language as we utilize it and and and
incorporate uh mappings to Concepts that
become generalized knowledge because
that knowledge enables us to to engage
with each other in a way that optimizes
technology and Tool use and our capacity
to engage with each other and make
abstract uh conceptualizations of the
world around us and
uh I could get really into that um um
but I spent a lot of time writing about
that but
uh that that uh that that's really what
makes us uniquely human now
okay maladaptive learning now has to do
with error prone habits and now getting
to
um the real issue with maladaptive
learning is what I like to
call
um uh well I don't know how many of you
are familiar with an non V's work uh an
non vadia uh brings up this interesting
concept known as cognitive strain so we
can think of like not just like you know
if you think about physics and forces
and how like applying stress like uh
let's say I take a wall and I throw it
at a wall and if I throw throw the ball
at a wall at the wall enough times it
creates a dent in the wall right so
likewise cognitive
strain uh we can consider that like the
amplif you know uh cognitive strain
could
be uh the problematic Association of
like what really makes maladaptive
learning an issue um that um this
prolonged exposure dist stressors that
compromises Fitness that compromises the
capacity for agents to have a a a
consistent World model and to um
leverage their capacity to to perceive
act and anticipate in a way that's
intuitive and and
unfortunately uh like excessive
cognitive overload uh compromises this
so um this goes into like you know uh
you know okay how do we facilitate that
well thinking about basic needs and what
have you and due to lack of time I'm not
going to get really into that but what I
will say um about cognitive strain is
like you know if if you over if the
agent is overloaded with with with
stressors like prolonged stressors right
and that contributes to to
trauma and we could think of trauma as
like being the result of this prolonged
exposure to to stressors and and that's
associated with the amplification and
magnification of of cognitive
strain um I would get more into
um in into into uh into addiction and
all that stuff and dealing with
addiction but uh I think that's more
more or less what
I've I've uh thrown together so far in
the body of my work I do however plan on
talking about Free Will Dynamics so to
summarize what I feel about uh what
makes Free Will relevant um my point on
Free Will is uh probably more on the
compatible is point of view where um we
consider degrees of freedom and
willpower
to uh align our perceptions actions and
priors with regard to uh constraints in
our environment that enables us to have
to make choices reflective of how we
feel with existing circumstances and how
those circumstances align in the future
and that moments of of of nondeterminism
really are uh become resolved when uh
choices reduce or evaluate to to how
certain certain certain decisions play
out and certain choices on line so uh
non-deterministic uh non non moments of
non-determinism become resolved into
deterministic actions over time based on
how choices play out reflective to uh
present moments of circumstances which
agents deal with that that carry over
and align with future scenarios that the
agent finds them themselves in so that
that was
another that that that's the last main
that has to do with the the the section
on Free Will that's the last main
section and then there's the conclusion
section of the paper of course I I also
have a modeling
section um I didn't expect to go over
models today but um I kind of elaborated
what my models would go over uh um but
um I think that more or
less
um talks about that more or less covers
uh you know there's a lot more I could
talk about but more or less um covers U
the work that I've been putting into
this this specific overiew paper of
habits and adaptive learning Dynamics
with respect to uh agents agal system
um yeah I I know I can go on and on and
thanks for that I just noticed that uh
message in the chat uh not terribly long
ago
but yeah well thank you Jesse let us
take a deep
breath okay yeah you covered a lot of
territory
I'll just read two questions from the
live chat just to note them and then
I'll just ask a final question and then
you can give a few minute response and
then we'll close
it okay so Michael Lennon wrote how
would he contrast the modification of
individual habits versus habits between
paired individuals versus habits of
clusters of individuals and Michael's
second question was how might he
describe how a moment of Novel
individual Insight becomes Collective
Behavior
change but just like to close it all out
overall where are you going to take this
work and H how do you intend to proceed
with
it right um so reflecting on Michael's
uh questions um so um let's address
those another time I know that you could
go into a lot of information on let's
just go right to the next steps yeah
yeah um so the next steps is um so this
current paper is really an overview of
um addressing what are what are habits
what is what do habits have to do with
adaptive learning and um how that ties
with agal systems and in the conclusion
section I'm going to bring about like
what's going to happen with the the the
next couple series of papers uh but
really um I was originally going to go
into the interventionary approach
approaches geared towards adaptive
learning but um so the next steps I want
to do with this work is uh go into the
interventionary approaches towards
adaptive learning so okay how can we use
technology how can we uh are there
different modes in which we can better
engage with information uh what about
just how we engage the world around us
like how like the food we eat like how
do we like are there ways that we
regulate food intake how about better
understanding reasoning and emotion like
how like is there some capacity in which
we can better uh how we can how we can
better reason with our emotions to more
have more effective reasoning
capacities to to deal with with
circumstances largely dealing with
non-triviality um so those are the those
are the four next papers I consider the
four Paradigm so the first Paradigm has
to do with technological interventions
like how can we utilize techn technology
to better uh facilitate how we engage
with the world around us and better
benefit not only our own agency but each
other's agency um and two would be
U uh mode uh Paradigm two has to do with
okay how can we better engage with
certain objects in the world like like
using tactile tools uh how can we use uh
different objects to facilitate how we
better engage with the world around us
uh three dieting Dynamics how how can we
leverage met abolism the most optimal
fashion to to to to to leverage agency
and for of course uh uh reasoning like
is there some means in which we can
better facilitate how we uh uh deal with
emo affective processing and and how
that can better be uh how reasoning can
be
better uh leveraged with better
understanding of deing with with
leveraging effective processing um so
that that's the next steps for me and
those are going to be individual papers
although I do have a uh I do plan on
talking about the different brain
regions so like a neuroscientific uh
more of a neuro
psychological uh approach in terms of
and going talking about the different
brain regions that are associated with
uh habits and adaptive learning and
agency but that would be a fifth paper
um um okay last question how could
people contact you or what would you
look to ask people for or how they could
get
involved um uh I uh I do have like a
business email but what I I'll I'll I'll
I'll have like an email where that uh
I'll provide a different email uh that I
can have people reach out to me uh by
it's it's a Google Mail account um so uh
reach out to me um and hopefully um uh
you know I I would love to try and
collaborate with the right parties um
and see where this work can go I I mean
I have a lot of uh confidence in terms
of especially with uh the system model
that I'm designing in terms of
technological interventions I would love
to talk to people about that uh because
that's the next main step I'm going with
is okay well there's a problem with how
we interface techn like with social
media and like just a lot of platform
like just a lot of basic Technologies
right now that really compromises how we
engage with you in with the world like
it's addictive like like social media is
addictive like people play mobile games
on their phone right right and that
people can waste hours doing all that
stuff so how can we better develop
systems that complement rather than
compromise our behavior um I think
that's really important to figure out um
and I would love to talk to more people
about that
um awesome well you covered a ton of
scope I hope that people who are
studying active inference see a lot of
the connections in the terms and topics
and systems and good luck in your
learning and
research thank you I appreciate it peace
Jesse
bye for